Guide to the Ireland House Oral History Collection AIA.030
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- G
  - Grange, Fr. Sean (John), Oct 29, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Fr. Grange describes going to school at St. Jerome’s, where he was taught by the Ursuline nuns for the first six years, and the De La Salle Christian Brothers until secondary school. At that time, St. Jerome’s was a growing parish with many vocations. He remembers that the priests had fancy cars and were very respected in the community. The only priest from Ireland in the parish left to go on a mission to Peru, where he was threatened by the terrorist group, the Shining Path, but survived to afterwards become the Chaplain of Cork University. Fr. Grange discusses another woman he knows who was killed by the Shining Path. Fr. Grange then returns to discussing his schooling, describing the brothers as very strict and penal. After graduating St. Jerome’s, Fr. Grange attended Cathedral Preparatory Seminary in Flushing, Queens, explaining that the students got off on Thursdays instead of Fridays, so that they could not attend dances. Fr. Grange’s twin brother, Joseph, left after the first four years of seminary school, but Fr. Grange stayed on. Before being ordained in 1966, Fr. Grange took a year off to teach English and History at Immaculata High School in Manhattan. After his ordination, Fr. Grange noticed other priests who were learning Spanish and working with the growing communities of Puerto Ricans, which influenced him to go to language school in Puerto Rico.
    After returning from Puerto Rico, Fr. Grange explains that he was assigned to work at St. Columba School in the Chelsea neighborhood of Manhattan. While there, he became more involved with the Puerto Rican community. After six years, Fr. Grange was transferred to Annunciation School in Harlem, which was a primarily Dominican community. When Annunciation was given over to Spanish priests, he took the opportunity to arrange a transfer to St. Jerome’s with the ambition of eventually becoming a pastor. In the 1980s, a large influx of Mexican immigrants started visiting him and attending church at St. Jerome’s. Fr. Grange describes how mass attendance continued to grow over the years despite the difficulties the undocumented Mexican immigrant community faced. Fr. Grange explains that in the late nineties, St. Jerome’s began to physically decay, prompting him to confront Cardinal Egan about funding for the renovation. Cardinal Egan decided to give St. Jerome’s the funding to renovate the Church, but three years later, he awarded the parish to a group of Argentinean priests and transferred Fr. Grange to St. Athanasius in the Bronx. Fr. Grange discusses the tension between the St. Jerome’s parish and their new priests that stems from their cultural and religious differences. Fr. Grange also mentions the problem of illegal immigrants wanting to get married, but not being able to under New York law. Fr. Grange’s new parish, St. Athanasius, is a mostly Puerto Rican community. He expresses concern for the parish, as most of the parishioners are elderly and oftentimes he performs several funerals a week.
    Fr. Grange explains that part of what has slowed him down recently has been an inflammatory disease called Polymyalgia Rheumatica, which causes severe pain in his back. He goes on to discuss how the changes made during Vatican II have made the Church more compassionate, but that not all religious have embraced the changes. Although there has been an increase in Spanish-speaking priests in the archdiocese, many have not fully invested in the communities they serve. Fr. Grange expresses concern about recently installed Cardinal Timothy Dolan, considering the problematic relationship former Cardinal Egan had with the priests. Fr. Grange goes on to discuss the problematic role of Pope Benedict XVI and the schism in the Church between those who agree with the Vatican II changes and those who do not. He mentions the lack of priests in the South Bronx, and the recent increase in violence.
    Then Fr. Grange discusses the community’s treatment of priests following the sexual abuse scandals. Fr. Grange comments on the various ways the Church has attempted to improve awareness about sexual abuse. Although there have been some leadership problems and “joy” has left the Church as an institution, Fr. Grange fundamentally believes that God is in the Church.
    Then Fr. Grange goes on to describe a typical day in his life, which begins with Qigong, Tai-Chi, and meditation. Fr. Grange discusses his love for swimming and how he held the record in his age group for the 100-yard free-style for five consecutive years.
    Fr. Grange explains that he rarely visits his former parish at St. Jerome’s, except to perform occasional funerals or marriages. Although his family is Irish-American, Fr. Grange does not identify with them, but rather feels a stronger connection with the Mexican community. Then, turning to his former political involvement, Fr. Grange discusses his involvement with the South Bronx Churches, an ecumenical group founded to protect the rights and quality of life for residents of the South Bronx. One of their main causes was to build houses for people in need. Fr. Grange ends by relating a story about the destruction of Church property while he was protesting with South Bronx Churches against poor medical care at Lincoln Hospital, prompting him to write a letter to Cardinal John Joseph O’Connor.
    Father John Grange was interviewed on 29 October 2009 at Glucksman Ireland House at New York University by Caitlin O’Brien and Linda Dowling Almeida. The interview is 1 hour, 51 minutes long, and 39 seconds long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place on October, 2009.
    Fr. Sean (John) Grange (b. 1940) has served the Archdiocese of New York as priest and pastor since 1966. The grandson of immigrants, he was raised South Bronx. His ministry has included assisting immigrants, particularly in the Puerto Rican community.
  - Gray, Rita, Mar 26, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Rita Fahy Gray (b. Ballydavok, Co. Mayo, d. Astoria, Queens, 2012), one of nine children, emigrated to the US in 1938 at the age of 19, after spending a year and a half in Manchester, England. She met her Irish-American husband through her first job as a domestic in Manhattan and they raised three children in Queens.
  - Greene, John, Mar 27, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Some of the themes discussed in this interview include: being Irish in Vietnam; Greene's life in the Bronx for 2 years when he was approximately 12; and how the Irish-born express Irishness as opposed to Irish Americans.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 140 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place In New York City on March 27, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    John Greene (b. Cootehill, Co. Cavan, 1945), a lawyer with the U.S. Department of Justice and a Vietnam veteran, he emigrated to the U.S. with his parents in 1957.
  - Grimes, Claire (two interviews), Feb 4, 2009-Feb 11, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Claire Grimes (b. 1936), publisher of the Irish Echo newspaper, was raised in the Riverdale section of the Bronx, NY. With roots in County Westmeath and County Sligo, Ireland, she married John Grimes, whom she succeeded as publisher after his premature death in 1987. To commemorate the 150th anniversary of the Famine, she commissioned Patrick Cassidy’s Famine Remembrance symphony and premiered it in New York’s St. Patrick’s Cathedral in 1996.
    Some of the key themes discussed in this interview include: her first perception of Ireland on her first trip; death of JFK (track 6); Obama for blacks what JFK was for Irish Catholics; Claire grandmother’s (Delia Gilligan from Co. Westmeath) was probably an 1880s immigrant; Irish Echo newspaper; father was an alcoholic; changes in Ireland; ‘I didn’t realize that I had been raised in an Irish home’ (track 4, 7 mins); and the insular nature of Irish New York community when she was growing up--no one left to go to school away.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview took place over 2 sessions and is approximately 2 hours long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place in New York City on February 4 and February 11, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Grimes, Patrick H., Dec 5, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- H
  - Hamill, Peter, Oct 22, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Pete Hamill (b. 1935), a novelist, essayist, journalist, and Distinguished Writer in Residence at New York University. Raised in Park Slope, Brooklyn, NY, the son of immigrants from Belfast, he was editor-in-chief of both the New York Post and the New York Daily News, and a columnist for both as well as for New York Newsday, the Village Voice, New York magazine and Esquire. His 1994 memoir, A Drinking Life, was on the same New York Times best-seller list for 13 weeks.
  - Hanley, Tom, Nov 5, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Tom Hanley (b. Jersey City, New Jersey, 1939), raised in Hoboken and a longshoreman since age 17, has been very involved with waterfront union politics. At age 14 he made an appearance in the film classic On the Waterfront (1954), directed by Elia Kazan.
  - Hartigan, Daniel (two interviews), Mar 29, 2008-Dec 9, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Daniel Hartigan, Jr. (born 1926), is an Irish immigrant, born in Limerick, whose father was an ardent follower of Eamon De Valera. His dad's allegiance to De Valera through the 1920s and 1930s cost him and the family dearly. Hartigan Sr.'s political choices led to financial and social reverses for the family and ultimately the migration of Daniel, Jr. and most of his siblings. Life for this IRA family in the west of Ireland during the 20s and through World War II offered few other options.
  - Haughey, Philip C., Apr 10, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    Philip C. Haughey (b. Waltham, MA, 1935) has served as Chair of Celtic Studies at his alma mater, Harvard University, on the board of University College Dublin's Smurfit School of Business in Ireland, and was awarded an honorary doctorate in 2005 from the University of Ulster, Coleraine, for his contribution to business and support for philanthropic organizations.
  - Hayes, Catriona, Mar 9, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Catriona Hayes (b. Cahirciveen, Co. Kerry, Ireland, 1974), a homemaker and a student nurse, emigrated to New York in 2000 after spending a period studying and working in London. She is married to Eddie Hayes.
    In this oral history, Hayes focuses on several topics, including: differences between Irish-born and Irish Americans, the latter assuming that children should attend Catholic school; difference between New York and London; dealing with Irish Americans in Irish pubs in New York (e.g. ‘Maggie’s Place’); her son growing up American; and changes in Ireland.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 80 minutes long, on 1 CD. The interview took place in Bellerose Terrace, New York, on March 9, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Hayes, Eddie, Mar 9, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Eddie Hayes (b. Co. Limerick, Ireland, 1966), a narcotics detective with the New York City Police Department, emigrated in 1989. After service with the U.S. Navy, he joined the NYPD in 1996. He is married to Catriona Hayes.
    Some key themes that Hayes discusses in this history are: being Irish in the navy; racial dynamics of the navy; and being Irish in the NYPD and working in Harlem.
  - Hayes, Thomas, Jun 2, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is 1 hour, 22 minutes, and 11 seconds long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place in San Francisco, on June 2, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    Thomas F. Hayes (b. Co. Limerick, 1925, d. San Francisco, 2010) emigrated to California in 1949 and in 1958 started his own business there, Tom Hayes Plastering. He was a founding member of the All Ireland Social Club and the United Irish Cultural Club, as well as a longtime member of the San Francisco Gaelic Athletic Association. He was appointed a Director of the Bay Area Rapid Transit by San Francisco Mayor Joseph Alioto in 1974. He is the father of the San Francisco Fire Chief Joanne Hayes- White.
  - Hearn, Anne, Mar 31, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    Anne Hearn (b. Co. Longford, Ireland, 1943) emigrated to the United States in 1961 and began working at Verizon Communications until she retired in 1997. She is very involved in both the Longford Association and the United Irish Counties Association of New York.
  - Heffernan, Eileen Reilly, Jun 17, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Eileen Reilly Heffernan (b. Bronx, New York, 1962), a former member of the Peace Corps, has taught in Washington State and in the Bronx. She is the daughter of Eileen Reilly Mescall.
  - Henchy, Seamus, Apr 23, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    Seamus Henchy (b. Ennistymon, Co. Clare, Ireland, 1954) came to the United States in 1983 and has established a niche business in New York managing museum and gallery renovations.
  - Higgins, Brigid, May 5, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Brigid Higgins (b. Loughrea, Co. Galway, 1935), a former Dominican nun and New York City school teacher, emigrated to America twice: at age 9 and at age 53. She lived in Ireland between 1972-88, then returned to New York where she completed her MA in Education at Manhattan College in 1992 and became a bedside educator for Memorial Sloane Kettering.
  - Hurley, Patrick, Oct 31, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Patrick Hurley (b. Wellington, New Zeland, 1962), raised in County Cork, was a member of the New Irish generation who found himself in New York City in the 1980s as an "illegal" alien with few options to succeed in America without proper documentation. Along with a core group of partners, he helped to found the Irish Immigration Reform Movement in 1987 and lobbied successfully to change immigration law in the US with the passage of the Immigration Act of 1990 HR-4300 which granted thousands of non-preference visas to immigrants considered unfairly disadvantaged by previous legislation, many of whom were Irish.
- I
  - Isacsson, Fr. Alfred, Apr 29, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Fr. Alread Isacsson of the Carmelite Order (b. Brooklyn, New York, 1932, d. Middletown, New York, 2011) was a High School teacher and Principal at St. Albert's Junior Seminary in Middletown, New York and at Pope John Paul II High School in Boca Raton, Florida. He was also a Parochial Vicar and Pastor at Transfiguration Church in Tarrytown, New York. Fr. Isacsson drew upon the Carmelite Archives in a number of articles, papers and books that explored the Carmelite relationship of the Irish independence movement in the early 20th century.
  - Isaly, Rosalie, Jun 9, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Rosalie Isaly (b. Chicago, Illinois, 1943) was born into a family in the Chicago funeral parlor business. Her father was John Louis O'Hanley who took over operations from his father. One of seven children raised on the South Side, she attended Loyola College and studied art in Perugia, Italy, and French in Paris. After working in advertising and marketing in Chicago, she moved to New York where she raised her children and worked as an art teacher.
- J
  - Johnston, Lisa, Mar 26, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Lisa Johnston (b. 1966), an immigration lawyer in private practice in Yonkers, NY, is the great-granddaughter of immigrants from Co. Donegal. She was an instrumental member of the Irish Immigration Reform Movement and is a board member of the Emerald Isle Immigration Center.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 80 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place in New York City on March 26, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
- K
  - Keane, Maurice, Oct 24, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    Maurice "Moss" Keane (b. Castleisland, Co. Kerry, Ireland, 1960) developed a successful business in property renovation in Boston for which he has received numerous awards.
  - Kehoe, George, Jun 2, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    George Kehoe (b. Dallas, Texas, 1952) a 3rd generation Irish American, has worked as an actor, writer and teacher. He wrote and directed Hunger, a play based on the prison writings of 1981 Irish hunger striker Bobby Sands.
  - Kelleher, Erin, Jul 5, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Erin Kelleher (b. Mt. Kisco, New York, 1973), the grandchild of four immigrants from County Cork, is a pediatrician in Tuckahoe, New York. Her mother was raised in Jersey City; her father was a fifth grade teacher. A graduate of the University of Notre Dame, she studied medicine at Trinity College Dublin, where she met her Irish-born husband.
  - Kelleher, Margaret, Jul 30, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    Margaret Kelleher (b. Mallow, Co. Cork, Ireland, 1964) studied for a Ph.D. in English Literature at Boston College, returned to teach in Ireland in 1990, and in 2012 was appointed Chair of Anglo-Irish Literature at University College Dublin.
  - Kelly, Catherine, Apr 24, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    Catherine Kelly (b. Carrickmore, Co. Tyrone, Northern Ireland, 1962) was a Morrison Visa recipient who grew up in Northern Ireland. She teaches Political Science and is active in Sinn Fein.
  - Kelly, Donald A., Nov 15, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Donald Kelly (b. 1935), is a retired Senior Vice President of Emigrant Savings Bank and President of the Executive Committee of the Emerald Isle Immigration Center.
  - Kelly, Patrick, M.D., Jan 17, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview took place in New York City on January 17, 2009, and the interviewers Myriam Nyhan and Marion Casey.
    Patrick J. Kelly (b. 1941), a neurosurgeon and Chairman of the Department of Neurological Surgery at NYU Langone Medical Center. Third generation Irish raised in Lackawanna, New York, he pioneered Computer-Assisted Stereotactic Neurosurgery and founded the New York-based charity the Brain Tumor Foundation.
  - Kelly, Ray, Nov 19, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Ray Kelly (b. Manhattan, 1941) is Commissioner of the New York City Police Department (1992-1994; 2001-present). He is a Vietnam veteran and retired Marine Colonel, with advanced degrees from St. John's University, New York University and Harvard. As a second-generation Irish American with ties to Counties Cavan, Roscommon, and Longford, Kelly served as Grand Marshal of the 2010 New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade. His brother is Don Kelly.
  - Kelly, Sr. Theresa, Nov 8, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Sister Theresa begins the discussion with a description of her parents lives in Ballinlough, County Roscommon, Ireland. She includes information such as what life was like there in general, as well as the work involved with owning a family farm. She recalls that her parents lived on the same street but came over to America separately and for different reasons in the early 1920s.
    Sister Theresa talks about her parents’ occupations after arriving in America. Her mother worked as a housekeeper and was later promoted to cook. Her father’s occupation as a police officer in combination with her mother’s strong money management enabled the couple to buy their own home. This was the house that Sister grew up in the Brooklyn, New York neighborhood of Bushwick with her two older siblings, James and Mary Anne. When Sister was five, her older brother left to attend the seminary, St. Joseph’s College in Princeton, New Jersey, eventually fulfilling his passion and becoming ordained as a Vincentian priest. Sister explains the differences between Vincentian and diocesan priests, and goes on to describe a typical day for a priest and his duties in general.
    Sister Theresa attended the single-sex Catholic educational institution St. John the Baptist grammar school. She went on to attend Bishop McDonnell Memorial High School in Brookyln, also a single-sex Catholic school. Sister Theresa mentions that being around religious figures her whole life played a part in motivating her to become a nun. However, after graduating in 1952, she was not yet sure of what she wanted to do, and went on to work in the accounting department at Pfizer Incorporated. After five years, in 1957, Sister Theresa chose to join the Brooklyn Sisters of Mercy. She talks about her various assignments at different schools, ranging from her first teaching assignment in Sunnyside, Queens, to a librarian at St. Patrick’s on Kent Avenue in Brooklyn, as well as her work as principal at Our Lady of Refuge in East Flatbush, Brooklyn.
    It was during her assignment at St. Patrick’s on Kent Avenue that Vatican II occurred. Sister Theresa describes the changes she saw in the Church, the effects the movement had on Catholic educations and the habit, as well as on the convent itself and the women within it. Sister’s opinion of the reforms were mostly negative. She believes that before Vatican II the women in the convent had a strict schedule that was followed, and without that kind of structure the women felt lost; she points to this as one of the changes that provoked many women to leave. She also disliked the changes in the habit. She discusses in detail the full habit nuns used to wear before Vatican II, as well as why she enjoyed wearing it and why she still wears the modified habit today, even though it is not a requirement. However, she does mention that she enjoyed the new freedom nuns had to vacation and visit family whenever they chose, as compared to before when time away from the convent was limited. She describes her family’s home in Breezy Point, Queens, and the joy it brought her to be able to go back there for vacations. Sister also discusses the effects Vatican II had on the convent, the Church and religion in general, as well as its impact on Catholic educations.
    Sister Theresa also discusses her Irish identity throughout the interview. She remembers listening to the Irish radio stations with her mother, and mentions that her sister took Irish dancing classes. She describes her Irishness as being inherent, and something that has always simply been a part of her. When asked about her Irish-American identity she explains that although she does not necessarily think about it, she knows she is Irish, and describes herself as more Irish than American, but that the greatness of America is also simply a part of who she is.
    Sister Theresa ends with a discussion about her current position at Our Lady of Mercy Academy in Syosset, New York, as event coordinator, where she organizes school events and fundraisers. She mentions the various events she handles yearly and the amount of money raised at some of them.
    This oral history with Sister Theresa Kelly was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview is 2 hours, 28 minutes long, on 3 CDs, and has been logged at ten minute intervals. Sister Theresa Kelly was interviewed on November 8, 2007, at Glucksman Ireland House at New York University by Kristina Galati, Linda Dowling Almeida, and Joseph Ready.
    Sr. Theresa Kelly (b. 1934) a member of the Sisters of Mercy of the Mid-Atlantic Community who, after a long teaching career, retired as Principal of Our Lady of Refuge in East Flatbush, Brooklyn (NY).
  - Kelly, Thomas, Dec 14, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    The interview is approximately 1 hour, 36 minutes long. The interview took place on December 14, 2005, and the interviewers were Tess Sheridan and Linda Dowling Almeida.